A Finding Aid to the Freda Koblick Papers, 1934-2011, in the Archives of American Art AAA.koblfred
Archives of American Art
Freda Koblick papers
1934-2011
AAA.koblfred
Archives of American Art
4.8 Linear feet
The papers of sculptor Freda Koblick measure 4.8 linear feet and date from 1934 to 2011. The collection documents her career through scattered biographical material, correspondence with family and friends, personal business records, writings, printed material, artwork, and photographs.
Koblick, Freda
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated in 2012 by Freda Koblick via Julia Fremon, Freda Koblick Living Trust.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 7 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1942-2011 (5 folders; Boxes 1, 6)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1934-2007 (1.5 linear feet; Boxes 1-2)
Series 3: Personal Business Records, circa 1950s-2009 (1.7 linear feet; Boxes 2-4, OV 7)
Series 4: Writings, circa 1962-1998 (0.2 linear feet; Box 4)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1943-1990 (0.3 linear feet; Boxes 4, 6)
Series 6: Artwork, circa 1950s-1980s (1 folder; Box 4)
Series 7: Photographs, circa 1930s-2007 (1 linear foot; Boxes 4-6)
Scope and Contents note
The papers of sculptor Freda Koblick measure 4.8 linear feet and date from 1934 to 2011. The collection documents her career through scattered biographical material, correspondence with family and friends, personal business records, writings, printed material, artwork, and photographs.
Scattered biographical material includes resumes and awards. Family correspondence includes many letters from her brothers David and Daniel. General correspondence is primarily personal correspondence with friends. Personal business records consist of Koblick’s files on commissions, exhibitions, travels, grants, sales, and publicity. Writings include 11 notebooks and loose notes. Printed material includes news clippings and exhibition announcements as well as printed material of interest to Koblick, but not directly documenting her career. Artwork consists of a small grouping of pencil sketches, possibly depicting her sculpture designs. Photographs depict Koblick, her family, friends, and artwork.
Biographical/Historical note
Freda Koblick (1920-2011) was a sculptor in San Francisco, California. Koblick attended San Francisco City College and San Francisco State College. She then moved to Los Angeles and received a certificate as a plastics engineer in 1943 from the Plastics Industries Technical Institute. She worked only in plastics as a medium for sculpture, with an emphasis on cast acrylic. At the start of her career she focused on designing and producing functional cast plastic objects such as doors, lighting, doorknobs, and fountains often in collaboration with architects.
By the 1960s Koblick was exhibiting her sculptures and was regularly teaching, lecturing, and offering workshops on plastics sculpture. From 1965 to 1967 she was a Senior Research Fellow at the Royal College of Art, London, where she set up the Experimental Plastics Unit and taught plastics theory and application. During the 1970s she received several large scale commissions, most notably a sculpture for the North Terminal of the San Francisco International Airport. In 1980 she moved into a former synagogue in the Mission District of San Francisco where she had a large studio and living space. She continued producing new artwork until she was in her mid-80s, at which point her health limited her ability to work.
Koblick, Daniel; Koblick, David; Photographs; Sculptors -- California -- San Francisco; Sketches; Women artists -- California
- Biographical Material, 1942-2011; Series 1; 5 Folders Boxes 1, 6
  Scope and Contents note
  Found here are biographical documents regarding Freda Koblick, including her obituary and a selection resumes, award certificates, and identification and membership cards. Also found are a few documents belonging to other Koblick family members.
  - Identification and Membership Cards, circa 1990s-2010 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Koblick Family Documents, 1946-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Obituary, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Resumes, 1970s; 1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Award Certificates, 1942; 1962 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1934-2007; Series 2; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Correspondence is arranged into two subseries: Family Correspondence and General Correspondence. Family correspondence is primarily from the 1940s and 1950s. Included are many letters sent by Daniel and David Koblick, Freda’s brothers, to family while they were serving in World War II. Also included are letters from Freda to her family and letters to her from her brothers and father, Morris. A small number of letters to Morris and his wife Rae from others are also found here.
  General correspondence is mostly of a personal nature, including letters to Freda from friends. A small amount of professional correspondence is also found here. Additional professional correspondence is included within Series 3: Personal Business Records.
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged as 2 subseries:
  2.1: Family Correspondence, 1934-1996
  2.2: General Correspondence, 1938-2007
  - Family Correspondence, 1934-1996; 2.1
    - Daniel Koblick Letters to Family, 1955-1959; 1945-1946; 1943 (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
    - David Koblick Letters to Family, 1936; 1955; circa 1961; 1934; 1943-1947 (Box 1, Folder 8-13)
    - Freda Koblick Letters to Family, 1952-1954; 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 14-16)
    - Daniel Koblick Letters to Freda Koblick, 1959-1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - David Koblick Letters to Freda Koblick, 1961-1996 (Box 1, Folder 18-20)
    - Morris A. Koblick Letters to Freda Koblick, 1963-1970 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence between Morris A. and Rae Koblick, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Morris A. and Rae Koblick Correspondence with Others, 1951-1961 (Box 1, Folder 23-25)
    - Holiday Cards, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - General Correspondence, 1938-2007; 2.2
    - American Craftmen's Council, 1960; 1965 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - American Institute of Architects, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Arnautoff, Victor M., 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - A, Miscellaneous, 1965-2005 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Bendien, Just, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Braun, Murray, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Breskin, Charles, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - B, Miscellaneous, 1963; circa 1970-1995 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Cancogni, Franca, 1973-1989 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Cummings, John and Kaye, 1968-1987 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - C, Miscellaneous, 1964-1998 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Davis, Jane, circa 1949-1980 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - DeVillar, Liv, circa 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - D, Miscellaneous, circa 1973-1984 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - E, Miscellaneous, 1963-1986 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Froud, Nina, circa 1955-1978; 1986 (Box 1, Folder 42-43)
    - F, Miscellaneous, 1957-1995 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Galerie Bouma, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - G, Miscellaneous, 1961-1980 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Harris, Henrietta, 1951; 1955-1976; 1995 (Box 1, Folder 47-56)
    - H, Miscellaneous, 1964-1987 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - I-J, Miscellaneous, 1966-1984 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Karasik, Bereni, 1963-1970 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - K, Miscellaneous, circa 1963-1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Long, Trevor, circa 1964-1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - L, Miscellaneous, 1968-1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Musgrave, Thea, circa 1967-1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - M, Miscellaneous, 1955-1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Narmour, Kathryn, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - N-O, Miscellaneous, 1964; circa 1979-1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - P-Q, Miscellaneous, 1964; 1974-1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Rider, J., 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Rukeyser, Muriel, 1948-1978 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - R, Miscellaneous, 1965-1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Samson, Frederic, 1964-1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Stanley, Peter, 1968-1984 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Steffens, Pete, circa 2000 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - St. Armand, 1968-1987 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - S, Miscellaneous, circa 1968-2007 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - T-V, Miscellaneous, 1970-1997 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Watterston, Henning, circa 1968-1990 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Weldon, Estela d'A., 1967-1982 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - West, Marie Welch, 1938; 1951-1975 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - West, Mariquita, 1987; 1964-1976 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Winfield, Armand, 1963-1969 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Wollitz, Ken, circa 1963-1968 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - W-Y, Miscellaneous, circa 1964-1986 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - First Names Only, A-Z, 1958-2003 (Box 2, Folder 25-32)
    - Unidentified and Illegible Names, circa 1950-1980 (Box 2, Folder 33-34)
- Personal Business Records, circa 1950s-2009; Series 3; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 2-4, OV 7
  Koblick’s personal business records document her work as a sculptor. Included are her files regarding commissions, exhibitions, travels, grants, artwork sales, and publicity. Of note are extensive commission files for her sculpture at the San Francisco airport, including contracts, photographs, fabrication plans, and legal records. Also of note is an interview transcript and related correspondence for an article about Koblick in Craft Horizons.
  - Addresses and Mailing Lists, circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Architectural Commissions, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Business Cards, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - California Arts Council Maestro-Apprentice Program, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Check Stubs, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 39-40)
  - Commission Lists, circa 1962 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Commission, Pennsylvania Ballet, 1977-1980 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Commission, Rohm and Haas Company, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 43-45)
  - Commission, San Francisco Airport, 1977-1983 (Box 3, Folder 1-12)
  - Commission, San Francisco General Hospital, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Craft Horizons Article, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Exhibits through 1962, 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
  - Exhibitions, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Exhibition, Philadelphia Art Alliance, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Exhibition, "Living Treasures of California", 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Exhibitions, Current and Pending, 1986-1994 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Europe, 1963; circa 1977 (Box 3, Folder 21-22)
  - Fairfax Property, 1959-1984 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Grant Applications, 1963-1969 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Guggenheim Fellowship, 1969-1971 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Hereward Lester Cooke Foundation, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Insurance Documents, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Lectures and Workshops, 1963-1966 (Box 3, Folder 28-29)
  - Lee Nordness Galleries, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Ministry of Labour Permit, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - New York Trip, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 32-33)
  - Plans for Convention Foyer, Inn on the Park, circa 1962 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Oversized material housed in OV 7.
  - Proposals and Contracts for Work on Property, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Sales Records, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 36-39)
  - San Francisco Art Commission, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Shop Log Book, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Sold Pieces, 1977-1980 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Studio Sale, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Tiffany Grant, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Travel, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Woman's Day Article, 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Oversize Plans for Convention Foyer, Inn on the Park, circa 1962 (Box OV 7)
    Oversized material from Box 3, Folder 34.
- Writings, circa 1962-1998; Series 4; 0.2 Linear feet Box 4
  Writings consist of eleven notebooks and notes on scraps of paper. Some notebooks only contain entries on a few pages while others include to-do lists, contacts, project notes, and small design sketches.
  - Notebook, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Notebook, circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Notebook, circa 1979 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Notebook, circa 1980 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Notebook, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Notebook, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Notebook, circa 1998 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Notebooks, undated (Box 4, Folder 9-12)
  - Notes, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Printed Material, 1943-1990; Series 5; 0.3 Linear feet Boxes 4, 6
  The small amount of printed material in this collection includes exhibition announcements and news clippings documenting Koblick’s career and the work of other artists. Additional programs, brochures, cards, and miscellaneous printed items were collected by Koblick but do not directly document her career as a sculptor.
  - Booklets on Woodworking Materials, 1947; 1962 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Cards from Antiquarian Book Fair, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Event Programs and Announcements, 1946-1990 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Oversized material housed in Box 6, Folder 2.
  - Exhibition Announcements, circa 1951-1986 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - News Clippings, circa 1946-1971; 1980 (Box 4, Folder 18-21)
  - Travel Brochures, circa 1960s (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1943-1988 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Oversize Event Programs and Announcements, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Oversized material from Box 4, Folder 16.
- Artwork, circa 1950s-1980s; Series 6; 1 Folders Box 4
  Found here is one folder of unidentified pencil sketches which may be preliminary designs for sculptures.
  - Sketches, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Photographs, circa 1930s-2007; Series 7; 1 Linear feet Boxes 4-6
  Included are photograph portraits of Freda Koblick, as well as photographs of her with family, friends, at a few events and in her studio. The bulk of the photographs depict her artwork either during fabrication or after installation. Slides mostly depict artwork but also include a few images of Koblick. Additional photographs are included within the commission files in Series 3: Personal Business Records.
  - Freda Koblick, circa 1940s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 25-27)
    Oversized material housed in Box 6, Folder 3.
  - Freda Koblick with Others, circa 1930s-2007 (Box 4, Folder 28-29)
  - Photographs of Others, circa 1940s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 30-31)
  - Exhibition at Magnes Museum, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous Personal Photographs, circa 1960s (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Miscellaneous Studio Shots, circa 1970s-1992 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Sculpture Fabrication, circa 1970s (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Technique Samples, circa 1960s (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Artwork - Bank of California, circa 1961 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Artwork - David's Restaurant, undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Artwork - Early Functional Small Pieces, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Artwork - Fountain for Vallejo Marina Vista, circa 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Artwork - Hardware, circa 1960s (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Artwork - International Building, San Francisco, circa 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Artwork - Morton Salt Building, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Artwork - "Sea Totem", circa 1990s (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Artwork - Studio Wall, circa 1960s (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Artwork - Miscellaneous, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 5, Folder 6-10)
  - Slides, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 5, Folder 11-14)
  - Oversize Photographs of Freda Koblick, circa 1940s-1970s (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Oversized material from Box 4, Folders 25-27.
  - Photograph Album of Artwork, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 6, Folder 4)